Primary keys in a table usually consist of a
single column. However, that is not always the
case. Let me show you one example. I am going to
select and hold (or right-click) this Person.Email
Address table and then choose Select Top 1000
Rows. This table stores email addresses that
belong to business entities. With every table, we
want to make sure we know the table's primary key.
Let's look at the logic of this table for just
a moment. Could a business entity have more than
one email address? Absolutely. Could two business
entities, like two people in the same business,
share an email address? While that is unlikely,
it is certainly possible. What is done, then,
in situations like these? I will select and hold
(or right-click) the Person.EmailAddress table
and select Design. Note that the primary
key designation is assigned to both
the BusinessEntityID and EmailAddressID
columns. This situation is known as a
composite key or a compound key, a primary
key that is the combination of two or more
columns. What this is telling us is that the
BusinessEntityID by itself is not a primary key,
and neither is the EmailAddressID. A composite
or compound key says that the two combined
cannot be repeated within this table, which makes
sense because you would not want a duplicate entry
of someone's business and an email address.
However, as stated before, a business could
have multiple email addresses, and an email
address could be shared among multiple business
entities, though this would be rare. In those
situations, a composite or compound primary
key should be implemented. Keep in mind that you
could go years without seeing a setup like this
one in a real-life database. Still, it is good to
know this can be done and is necessary at times.